1701 E 8TH ST, #213

MANOJ SHANKAR A J

TEMPE, AZ-85281 https://www.linkedin.com/in/manoj-shankar-aj/

manandav@asu.edu +1-480-859-4007

SUMMARY

A technically sound computer science graduate student with 2 years of corporate experience in a global cloud company coupled with in-depth knowledge in Algorithms, Data Structures, Database systems and Full-stack development looking for Summer Internship opportunities in 2018.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages: Java, C++, Python, Javascript IDE/Tools: NetBeans, Eclipse, Visual Studio, GitHub, Mercurial, Jenkins

Web: HTML, CSS, Handlebars, JSP, jQuery, Ajax

Operating Systems: Windows(10,7), Linux, Mac OS X

EXPERIENCE

ZOHO CORPORATION, Chennai, India

Databases: MySQL, PostgreSQL, Redis

June 2015 - June 2017

Member Technical Staff

- Worked solo to develop a 'Mass Operations' framework for the cloud application Zoho CRM which lets users to perform bulk operations like updating, changing ownership of up to 100,000 records in a module.
- Developed the scheduling mechanism to perform these heavy DB related processes with minimal load on the application server.
- Developed the complete back-end code in **Java** along with constructing optimized queries to fetch the huge no of records using **PostgreSQL.**
- Showed the live progress of the running and scheduled jobs to the users using Javascript, jQuery, Ajax, and Handlebars.
- Developed Translation Platform for Zoho CRM which enables users add new languages and translations to the Zoho CRM application
- Analysed and used Redis as a cache to efficiently store and quickly retrieve the translations provided by the user.
- Developed the back-end code in Java to apply the user provided translations efficiently across the whole CRM web application.
- Developed new features in the Zoho CRM Plugin for Microsoft Outlook using C# which enables synchronization of Contacts, Tasks,
 Events between Zoho CRM and Outlook.

SAMSUNG RESEARCH & DEVELOPMENT INSTITUTE, Bangalore, India

May 2014 - July 2014

Summer Intern

- Worked in the IMS-Media Team, the team that manages the Samsung VolTE stack.
- Learnt the architecture of the IMS-Media Framework Client, the VoIP and its component protocols like Session Initiation Protocol (SIP), Real-time Transport Protocol(RTP), Real-time Transport Control Protocol(RTCP) etc.
- Learnt in detail the inner workings of a video call in Samsung mobile over LTE and studied the various color models like RGB, YUV, YCbCr and **implemented conversions of a frame** from one color model to another in C.
- Developed a new feature in the video chat application of Samsung S5 mobile by **developing and implementing image processing algorithms** in **C** which enables users perform various interactive animations on the participants during the video chat using DTMF.

EDUCATION

MASTERS IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

Arizona State University, USA

Aug 2017 - May 2019 (expected)

B.TECH - INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY

CGPA: 8.12/10

Madras Institute of Technology, Anna University, Chennai, India

Aug 2011 - April 2015

ACADEMIC PROJECT

Adaptive video streaming over HTTP employing dynamic on the fly bitrate analysis

Jan 2015 - March 2015

- The aim was to **implement an adaptive client-server video streaming system** in which the client analyses the bit rates on the fly and sends a feedback to the server which in turn changes the frame rate and quality of the video to maintain smooth video playback.
- **Developed a mathematical model** to judge the bandwidth conditions from the incoming bit-rates and incorporated it in **an intelligent algorithm at the client** to analyse the incoming video stream.
- Implemented the algorithm in Java employing multi-threading concepts achieving avg PSNR of 36.267 and SSIM of 0.9683.

PUBLICATIONS

• Dhananjay Kumar, Nandha Kishore Easwaran, A. Srinivasan, A. J. Manoj Shankar, L. Arun Raj. "Adaptive video streaming over HTTP through 3G/4G wireless networks employing dynamic on the fly bitrate analysis". ITU Kaleidoscope: Trust in the Information Society (K-2015), Barcelona, Spain, December 9-11, 2015, Published in IEEE Xplore.